And at last the time has come to see rag in action.
마침내 래그가 활약하는 걸 보러 왔죠
After all of this talk, and here we are.
그렇게 떠들어대더니 결국 이렇게 됐네요
We're in, of course, the week five folder in JupyterLab.
주피터랩의 5주 차 폴더에 있어요
We're looking at day four, the notebook, and it is, of course a duplicate of day three with more
4일째인 노트북을 보고 있는데요 3일째에 추가된 걸 복제한 거예요
Since we're still solving the same problem of a knowledge worker for our fictitious insurance tech company
가상의 보험 기술 회사의 지식 노동자 세럼의 문제를 여전히 해결하는
in serum.
중이니까요
Uh, and we will start with the usual imports as before.
기존의 수입품부터 시작할 거예요
And now we have some imports for Lang chain, and I have sneakily added in two new imports from Lang
랑체인용 수입 기능도 추가했는데요 랑체인 메모리에서 두 가지를 추가했어요
We're importing conversational buffer memory.
대화 버퍼 메모리를 불러올게요
And from Lang chain chains we're bringing in conversational retrieval chain.
랭 체인에서 대화용 회수 체인을 가져왔어요
And these are two of the abstractions that I mentioned before.
이건 제가 전에 언급한 추상화 두 가지인데요
Now the astute amongst you will have noticed that the third abstraction is also lurking in here.
눈치 빠른 분들은 눈치챘겠지만 세 번째 추상화도 여기 들어 있어요
I just already imported it in one of our previous lectures without mentioning it, but here it is.
이전 강의에서 언급하지 않고 이미 불러왔지만 여기 있네요
Chat OpenAI is already being imported as part of from Lang chain.
챗 오픈아이는 이미 랑가 체인에서 수입되고 있어요
OpenAI, uh, we've only been using so far the OpenAI embeddings, but this time we're going to bring
오픈AI, 지금까지 오픈AI 엠딩만 사용했는데 이번에는 채팅 오픈AI를
chat OpenAI into the mix.
사용할 거예요
Okay, so I better run those imports.
수입 검사를 해 봐야겠어요
Otherwise we're not going to get very far.
Get it 안 하면 멀리 못 가요
So then we do some constants.
그런 다음 상수를 하죠
We load our environment variables.
환경 변수를 로드해요
And now you're quite familiar with this.
이제 익숙해질 거예요
But we go through and we bring in our documents from the knowledge base directory over there.
하지만 검토하고 저기 있는 지식 기반 디렉터리에서 문서를 갖고 오죠
And now we're going to bring in the text chunks the let's see how many.
이제 텍스트 덩어리를 갖고 와서 얼마나 많은지 보죠
But I do believe it's 123.
123번인 건 확실해요
Yes, 123 text chunks.
네, 123개요
And they are employees, products companies and contracts.
직원, 제품 회사, 계약이죠
And now we're going to again put them into our vector database.
이제 다시 벡터 데이터베이스에 Put을 할게요
We delete and recreate the vector database.
벡터 데이터베이스를 삭제하고 다시 생성하죠
And we see that each vector has 1536 dimensions.
각 벡터는 1536개의 차원을 가지고 있죠
Hard for us to visualize, but we can handle it in 2D.
상상하긴 어렵지만 2D로 처리할 수 있어요
So that's what we do.
그게 우리 일이죠
And there they are.
저기 있네요
And we can also say let's see it in 3D as well.
3D로 보자고 할 수도 있어요
This is a little bit gratuitous.
비트가 좀 불필요하네요
I didn't need to go through and rerun all of this, but I do love seeing these these diagrams.
이걸 전부 다시 볼 필요는 없었지만 이 도표들을 보니 좋네요
All right, so here, I didn't lie to you.
난 거짓말한 적 없어요
It really is as simple as these four lines of code.
이 코드 네 줄만큼 간단해요
We first create the new LM abstraction.
먼저 새 LM 추상화를 생성하죠
We the chat OpenAI.
채팅방 오픈라이예요
We're going to put that that thing we've imported for a while.
아까 가져온 것을 put을 거예요
We're going to put it to use finally.
드디어 그걸 쓸 수 있게 됐죠 Put it up Put it up Put it up Put it up Put it up Put it
And you supply a temperature and a model name, uh, memory.
온도와 모델명 메모리를 제공해요
We create the conversational buffer memory passing in, as I mentioned before, the key and saying we
전달되는 대화 버퍼 메모리를 생성합니다 아까 말씀드렸듯이 키를 생성하고
want it returned in the form of a, of a list.
목록의 형태로 반환하라고 하죠
Uh, we take our chroma vector store and we call as retriever to sort of wrap it in this abstraction,
크로마 벡터 스토어를 가져와서 리트리버를 호출합니다 이 추상화, 리트리버에서 래핑하기
the retriever, which is needed by Lang chain.
위해서요 랭 체인에 필요한 거죠
And that is where we now get to when we create the conversational retrieval chain.
그래서 지금 대화 회수 체인을 만들 때 거기에 도달하는 거죠 get it
And we simply pass in the LM, the retriever and the memory.
LM, 리트리버, 메모리를 전달하는 거죠
That's all it is.
그게 다예요
Let's run that.
실행해 보죠
Okay.
네
So we ran it.
그래서 실행했죠
Perhaps a slight anticlimax.
살짝 실망스럽긴 하지만요
I'm not sure what you're expecting, whether you thought maybe we were going to get suddenly rag appearing
뭘 기대하셨는지 모르겠지만요 갑자기 get이 나타날 거라고 생각하셨는지
in front of us.
모르겠네요
We have to actually call it.
실제로 호출해야 해요
We have to do something to make use of it.
그걸 활용할 방법을 찾아야 해요
So what we're going to say is we're going to say, um, um, query calls.
그래서 우리가 하려는 말은 쿼리 호출이라고 하죠
Uh, can you describe in short film in a few sentences, a nice we will start simple.
짧은 영상으로 짧게 설명해 주시겠어요? 간단하게 시작할게요
All right.
좋아요
And this is what you say.
이렇게 말해요
You say result is conversation chain.
결과가 대화의 사슬이라고 하셨죠?
The thing that we've just created and we call the method invoke.
방금 생성한 거요 메서드 호출이라고 부르죠
And invoke takes a dictionary which has question as a key.
인보크는 질문이 열쇠인 사전을 선택해요
Did I spell that right?
철자가 맞나요?
Yes.
네
Question.
질문 있어요
And we have to put in our message query.
그리고 메시지 쿼리를 입력해야 해요 Put
And there we have it.
다 됐어요
And then we're going to print result.
그런 다음 print결과를 하죠
This should be something under the key of answer in that result.
이건 그 결과의 해답 키 아래에 있어야 해요
So this then is the final piece of code that we put together to try and make use of our Rag pipeline.
이게 우리가 합친 마지막 코드입니다 래그 파이프라인을 사용하기 위해서요
So what do we think is going to happen?
어떻게 될 것 같아요?
It's going to take that query.
쿼리를 가져가요
It's going to turn that into a vector.
벡터로 바꿀 거예요
It's going to look that up in our Chrome data store.
크롬 데이터 스토어에서 찾아볼 거예요
It's going to find relevant chunks.
관련 있는 덩어리를 찾을 거예요
And I say chunks plural.
덩어리 복수형이라고 하죠
And we're going to come back to that.
그건 나중에 다시 얘기하죠
So it's going to find relevant chunks.
관련 있는 덩어리를 찾죠
And it's going to drop them into the prompt and send that to OpenAI.
프롬프트에 그걸 넣어 OpenAI에 보내죠
Uh, it's going to send it to GPT four mini because we've specified that here.
GPT for 미니로 보낼 겁니다 여기서 지정했거든요
And then with what comes back, it's going to package it up and put that in the answer key.
그리고 돌아온 것은 그것을 패키지로 해서 answer key에 두죠
Let's see if this works.
이게 통할지 보죠
There we go.
됐어요
We've just run our first Rag pipeline front to back in Shoreham.
쇼어햄에서 처음으로 래그 파이프라인을 탔어요
Innovative insurance tech firm founded by Avery Lancaster, a name we know well at this point and so
혁신적인 보험 기술 회사 에이버리 랭커스터가 설립했죠 지금도 잘 알려진 이름이에요
on.
정보도 좀 있고요
And I will leave this as an exercise for you to play around with, but you'll see that it's got that
여러분이 갖고 놀 수 있는 연습용으로 남겨두겠습니다만 다양한 문서에서
out from various documents, I think probably all from the about from the company section.
그걸 갖고 온 걸 보실 수 있어요 회사 섹션의 모든 것에서 나온 거겠죠
Uh, but, uh, I hopefully you'll see that it has retrieved that from various chunks of information.
다양한 정보로부터 그걸 검색한 걸 보셨으면 좋겠네요
All right.
좋아요
Well, wouldn't it be nice?
그럼 좋겠죠?
Do you know where this is going?
어떻게 될지 알아요?
Wouldn't it be nice if we could package that up into a beautiful user interface, so that we could actually
그걸 멋진 사용자 인터페이스로 패키지할 수 있다면 좋지 않을까요? 채팅
use it through a chat UI?
UI를 통해 사용할 수 있도록요
And of course, Gradio makes it super simple as well.
물론 그라디오는 아주 간단하게 만들고요
We know at this point all we have to do is create a chat function in the format that Gradio expects.
이 시점에서 우리가 할 일은 그라디오가 기대하는 포맷으로 채팅 함수를 만드는 거예요
That takes a message and a history.
그러려면 메시지와 역사가 필요하죠
So what I've done is I've taken exactly the line that we just wrote, and I've put it here, and then
제가 한 일은 방금 작성한 바로 그 줄을 취해 여기 둔 겁니다 그런 다음 우리가
I return exactly what we're expecting.
기대하는 걸 정확히 반환하죠
Now, you might see something curious about that, give you a moment to look at it and see anything,
뭔가 이상한 점이 보일 수도 있으니 잠시 시간을 두고 살펴보세요 뭔가 이상한
anything strike you as odd.
점이 보이나요?
Well, the one thing that might potentially strike you as odd is that we don't actually do anything
한 가지 이상하게 생각하실 만한 건 이 역사 매개 변수를
with this history parameter.
실제로 아무것도 안 한다는 거예요
Uh, we ignore it completely.
완전히 무시해요
And the reason we ignore it is because, of course, Lang Chain already handles history for us.
우리가 그걸 무시하는 이유는 랭 체인이 이미 역사를 다루기 때문이죠
So even though Gradio has this chat UI that calls that sort of maintains the history in the user interface,
그래디오에 채팅 UI가 있어서 사용자 인터페이스에서 대화 기록을 유지하고 매번 전체
and then calls back every time with the with the full chat history.
대화 기록과 함께 호출되지만 말이에요
We don't need that because because Lang has already given us this, this memory, and it's already keeping
랭이 이미 우리에게 메모리를 줬기 때문에 지금까지의 대화를
track of the conversation so far.
기록하고 있어요
All it needs to know is the new message and the new answer.
새 메시지와 새 답만 알면 돼요
So anyway, I'm rerunning the cell here.
어쨌든 이 감방을 다시 찍고 있어요
I actually already reran it, but I'm rerunning it to clean out the memory.
사실 이미 재실행했는데 메모리를 지우려고 재실행 중이에요
So we're starting absolutely fresh.
완전히 새롭게 시작하는 거죠
We call that we bring this up and now we can chat.
이걸 불러오면 이제 채팅할 수 있어요
Hi there.
안녕하세요
How can I assist you today?
무엇을 도와드릴까요?
What is insurance?
보험이 뭐죠?
Um.
네
There we go.
됐어요
No surprise.
놀랍지도 않네요
And now we can do something sneaky.
이제 몰래 뭔가 할 수 있어요
We can say something like.
이런 식으로요
What did Avery do before?
에이버리는 뭘 했죠?
And now the reason I'm, uh, I'm bringing this up is that there's a few things that I want to surface
제가 이 얘기를 꺼낸 이유는 이런 질문에서 몇 가지 짚고 넘어가고 싶은
in a question like this.
게 있어서예요
So first of all, to state the obvious, our brute force solution before our toy version of Rag was
먼저, 무력을 이용한 해결책이 명확합니다 장난감 버전 래그에서는 랭커스터를 성으로
able to look at Lancaster as a last name and search for that in documents, which was pretty hopeless.
보고 문서에서 검색할 수 없었지만 가망이 없었죠
And if we tried the word aviary, then it failed on us.
새장이라는 단어를 쓰면 안 돼요
So it's of course interesting to try it here.
여기서 시도하는 건 당연히 흥미롭죠
Secondly, I have intentionally put aviary with a lowercase a, because anything that's doing a kind
둘째, aviery를 소문자 a로 썼어요. 왜냐하면
of text search is going to get that wrong because aviary is uh, is spelt differently.
a는 철자가 다르기 때문에 텍스트로 검색하면 틀릴 테니까요.
So, uh, it'll be interesting to see whether it can handle the fact that we've not used the right case.
그래서 우리가 제대로 된 케이스를 사용하지 않았다는 사실을 감당할 수 있을지 보는 것도 흥미로울 거예요
And then thirdly, I'm sort of taking advantage of this memory idea because I'm referring to what she
세 번째는 메모리라는 개념을 이용하는 거예요 그녀가 전에 했던 걸 말하는
did before.
거니까요
Meaning what did she do before she founded in Elm.
엘름에 설립하기 전에 뭘 했는지 묻는 거예요
And we'll see whether the model is has a good enough sense of what's going on to be able to keep the
모델이 현재 상황을 잘 파악하고 맥락을 유지하는지 볼 거예요 조류 새장에
context, both retrieve relevant information about aviary and what she did before.
관한 정보와 이전 행동을 둘 다 검색할 수 있는지요
That will need to come from her employee record.
직원 기록에서 찾아봐야 해요
Uh, and also, uh, just answer the question in a coherent way.
그리고 일관성 있게 질문에 대답하세요
Let's see.
어디 보죠
Before founding in Shoreham, Avery Lancaster worked as a senior product manager at Innovate Insurance
쇼어햄에 입사하기 전 에이버리 랭커스터는 이노베이트 보험 솔루션스의 수석 제품 관리자로 일했습니다
Solutions, where she developed groundbreaking insurance.
혁신적인 보험을 개발한 곳이죠
Prior to that, business analyst focusing on market trends.
그 전에는 시장 경향에 초점을 맞춘 사업 분석가였죠
So I will leave it as an exercise for you to check her employee record and make sure that you're satisfied
그래서 여러분이 에이버리의 직원 기록을 확인하시도록
that it is indeed correctly finding it and getting the right background on Avery, uh, as a fun thing
남겨둘게요 그리고 에이버리의 신원을 제대로 파악하고 있는지 확인하세요 재미있는 실험이니까요
Um, and also, of course, try other difficult questions.
물론 다른 어려운 질문들도 시도해 보세요
Uh, what does, um.
무슨 뜻이죠?
Uh.
네
Let's see.
어디 보죠
Calm do that was the car, um, uh, product.
침착하게가 그 차의 제품이었어요
Um.
네
Or how about, um, let's ask it differently.
아니면 다르게 물어보죠
Let's say does insurance offer any products in the car in the auto Assurance space.
자동차 보험 회사에서 자동차에 제품을 공급하나요?
Let's give it a nice, tricky question.
까다로운 문제를 내 보죠
And there we go.
다 됐어요
Yes.
네
Insurance offers Calm, which is a portal for auto insurance companies.
자동차 보험 회사들을 위한 포털인 안정감을 주는 보험이죠
So it's able to even though I didn't use the word calm or even the word car, it was able to find the
그래서 제가 진정이나 자동차라는 단어를 사용하지 않는데도 관련 문서와 관련
relevant document, the relevant chunk, and answer the question in an accurate way.
덩어리를 찾아 정확한 답변을 할 수 있죠
So that is your first experiment with Rag.
랙으로 하는 첫 실험이었군요
I hope you will now try this.
이제 이걸 드셔 보세요
I hope you will investigate, ask difficult questions, find out if you can break it or get it to give
여러분이 수사하고 어려운 질문을 해서 그걸 깨뜨리거나 잘못된 정보를 제공할 수 있는지 알아내길
wrong information, or go off the rails and stretch it to its limits.
바랍니다 아니면 선을 벗어나 한계까지 밀어붙여 보세요 get it get it
Next time, amongst a few other things, we'll talk about some of the ways, some of the common problems
다음 시간엔 몇 가지 다른 걸 포함해 방법 몇 가지를 다루겠습니다 이런 종류의 프롬프트와 관련해
that you can get with these kinds of prompts, and how you can debug and find out more about what's
공통된 문제 몇 가지와 어떻게 디버그 하고 Get up 밑에서 무슨 일이 있는지
going on under the covers.
알아내는 방법도요
But I hope you enjoyed your first end to end rag pipeline built for our fictional insurance tech company
하지만 쇼어햄에 있는 우리 가상 보험 기술 회사를 위해 만든 래그 파이프라인을 즐겁게 보셨길
in Shoreham.
바라요
See you next time.
다음에 봐요